Guide to the Gary Cartwright Papers
The Wittliff Collections
Gary Cartwright Papers
1981-1999, undated
The Wittliff Collections
Cartwright, Gary, 1934-2017
SWWC.001
7 Linear Feet
16 boxes
The Gary Cartwright papers date from 1981 to 2000 and document his writing career.
Scope and Contents
The Gary Cartwright papers date from 1981 to 2000 and are organized into five series: 1.) Books, 2.) Plays, screenplays, and song lyrics, 3.) Articles, 4.) Correspondence, and 5.) Clippings. Included are handwritten notes, clippings, tear sheets, brochures, a cassette tape, drafts and galley proofs. The material describes the research and editing involved in Cartwright's writing process.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Source of Acquisition
Gifts of Gary and Phyllis Cartwright since 1989.
Biographical Notes
Gary Cartwright was born August 10, 1934 in Dallas, Texas, and raised in nearby Arlington. He received a B.A. in journalism and government from Texas Christian University in 1957. Cartwright reported the police beat for the Fort Worth Star-Telegram from 1956 until he was hired away in 1958 to the Fort Worth Press, where he joined Dan Jenkins and Bud Shrake in the sports department under legendary Texas sportswriter Blackie Sherrod. In 1960, Cartwright moved to the Dallas Times Herald as a sports reporter and in 1963 he joined the Dallas Morning News to write his own sports column. Cartwright's first book, a football novel entitled The Hundred Yard War, was published in 1967 at which point he left newspaper work to become a freelance writer. His work has appeared in The Texas Observer, Esquire, Saturday Review, Rolling Stone and Texas Monthly.
Cartwright has been associated with Texas Monthly magazine since its inception in 1973. His articles range over various topics--crime, notable Texans, Texas culture, travel, sports and international travel. A collection of his Texas Monthly articles can be found in Confessions of a Washed-up Sportswriter. The true-crime books Blood Will Tell and Dirty Dealing began as articles for Texas Monthly. In 1988, Cartwright had a heart attack that required quintuple-bypass surgery. A suggestion by Governor Ann Richards to document changes in his life since the injury led to his latest book, HeartWiseGuy.
Among the many honors Cartwright has received for his writing are the Texas Institute of Letters' Stanley Walker Award for Journalism for "The Endless Odyssey of Patrick Henry Polk" (Texas Monthly, May 1977) and the Press Club of Dallas Katie Award for Best Magazine News Story for "The Work of the Devil" (Texas Monthly, June 1989). Cartwright has written screenplays in collaboration with Edwin (Bud) Shrake, including .J W. Coop (1972) and Another Pair of Aces (CBS-TV, 1990).
Cartwright passed away on February 22, 2017.
Related Materials
See also Accession Numbers 88-052 and 90-071 for photographs of the author taken by Bill Wittliff.
Gonzo journalism; Authors, American -- Texas -- 20th century; Galveston (Tex.) -- History; Cartwright, Gary, 1934-2017
- Books, 1988-1999, undated
  Series Description
  This series is arranged chronologically by publication, with an unpublished title at the end. The first subseries is for the book, Galveston, a History of the Island. These files contain research material and an annotated typescript for the book. The files are organized according to the author's filing system, primarily in chronological order. They contain articles, clippings, handwritten notes, newsletters, brochures and tear sheets. There is information on social life, prominent Galveston families, ethnic groups and major events such as the 1900 hurricane.
  Material for the second book in this series, HeartWise Guy, spans 1988-1999. These files contain research material, drafts, annotated typescripts, and page proofs. The files are organized according to the author's filing system. They contain articles, clippings, handwritten notes, newsletters, brochures and tear sheets. Topics include aging, lifestyle, diet, medicine, sex, and spirituality. Also included is a letter from Larry McMurtry commenting on his long post-surgery depression following a heart attack.
  Materials for Blood will Tell are limited to only correspondence and clippings. And the unpublished title, "Black Pearls," or "Dark Pearls," is represented by an annotated typescript.
  - Galveston, a History of the Island, 1988-1991, undated
    - Handwritten notes (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - The Saccarappa, Galveston Historical Foundation Newsletter (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Empire Life Involuntary Petition (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Moody (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Open Beaches (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Galveston Mardi Gras & General (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
    - Barrier Islands (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Karankawas & Cabeza de Vaca (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Lafitte (Jean) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Republic of Texas (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Civil War (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Cuney & Blacks (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    - Gilded Age (1860-1900) (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
    - Seawall/Grade Raising (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Rabbi Cohen/Galveston Movement (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 1880-1890 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1880-1890--Albert Lasker/Jack Johnson (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1900 Hurricane and lesser blows (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - After 1900 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Moody, Kempner, Sealy (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Partners in Progress & Sociological Studies (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Gambling, Whoring, 1920s-1957 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Kempners (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Moodys 1860-1960 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
    - Blacks (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Moodys, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Interviews & Name (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Gaido & other interviews (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - GHF Galveston Historical Foundation (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Annotated typescript (Box 14, Folder 3-5)
  - HeartWiseGuy, 1988-1999, undated
    - Research Files, undated
      - Aging (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Alternatives (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - American Heart Association (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Anti-Aging Therapies (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Anti-Oxidants (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Attitude / Spiritual (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Diet and Nutrition (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Dr. Blevins (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Dr. Charles Wilkins (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Drugs, Alcohol, Smoking (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Exercise (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Health / Medical (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Herbs / Medicinal (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Hypertension, diabetes, osteoporosis, impotence… (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - Love / Sex (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Miscellaneous Clippings (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Pacemaker (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Research (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Sex (Dr. Kaufman) (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence with Larry McMurtry (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Drafts
      - Typescript with Dr. Blevins' edits (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Annotated typescript (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
      - Page proofs (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
  - Blood Will Tell, undated
    - Correspondence (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Clippings (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Black Pearls / Dark Pearls (unpublished), undated
    - Annotated Typescript (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
- Plays, Screenplays, and Song Lyrics, 1981-1991, undated
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material on screenplays in collaboration with Bud Shrake. There are handwritten song lyrics for Shrake's Pancho Villa's Wedding Day and one draft and two scripts of RIP on which the 1991 teleplay Another Pair of Aces was based. Also included is a ditty hastily composed by Gary Cartwright with Larry L. King late one night in New York City.
  See also Accession No. 88-033, 90-059, 91-007 for other material on RIP in the Bud Shrake and Bill Wittliff papers and Accession No. 92-061 for a Cartwright teleplay written for the Ned Blessing series.
  - Works by Cartwright
    - Pancho Villa's Wedding Day (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
    - RIP
      - Script (Box 5, Folder 1, Box 14, Folder 6)
      - Draft (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - Shooting schedule (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - Clippings (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Songs (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Works of Others (Based on or Inspired by Cartwright's Work)
    - "Another Pair of Aces" by Rob Gilmer (2 typescripts) (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - "Santos and Santos" by Octavio Solis (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Articles, 1985-1999
  This series is primarily composed of drafts and galley proofs for articles written for Texas Monthly. There is a good deal of research material for the 1987 article on the murder of a San Antonio policeman, "Total Hit." The articles report on crime, sports, food and prominent Texans. The files are arranged by date of publication when known.
  Articles not written for Texas Monthly are arranged in the subseries, General. This set of articles includes national and international sports culture and travel, and honest and dishonest personalities in Texas culture, art, prisons, and politics. An unpublished article on whistle blowing within several large federal law enforcement agencies is also included.
  - Texas Monthly Articles, 1985-1989
    - H. R. Bum Bright, Austin American Statesman. Port galley proof, July 7, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - The Last Roundup, February 1985 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - An Aggie's Revenge, August 1985 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - The Final Gun, September 1985 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Hugh Roy Cullen's Last Hurrah, January 1986 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Range Warrior, January 1986 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - The Snootiest Neighborhood in Texas, June 1986 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Touch Me, Feel Me, Heal Me, December 1986 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Total Hit, January 1987 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Cops (Total Hit), January 1987 (Box 5, Folder 12-14, Box 6, Folder 1-6)
    - Lifestyles, Home Ain't Where My Heart Is, March 1987 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - The Longest Ride of His Life, May 1987 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Texas Primer: Clint Murchison, Jr., June 1987 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - The Sleaziest Man in Texas, August 1987 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - I, Piscivore, September 1987 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Paradise Lost, October 1987 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Everyone a Victim, November 1987 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - An Old Five and Dimer, February 1988 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Newspapers (unpublished) (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Search and Destroy, March 1989 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Poisoned with Love, May 1989 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - The Work of the Devil, June 1989 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - How George Foreman Finally Beat Muhammed Ali, October 1989 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Old Salts and Ancient Mariners, October 1989 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Mean (unpublished) (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Articles, General, 1992-1999
    - Dawson, George, December 1998 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Diary of a Minor Mogul, June 1996 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Golfsmith / Karl Paul, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Marsh, Stanley, March 1978 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Masters Tickets, February 1998 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - McDuff, Kenneth, August 1992 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Mexican Road Race, 1999 (Box 12, Folder 3-4)
    - Moscow / National Geographic, 1999 (Box 12, Folder 5, Box 13, Folder 1-6)
    - Old Five and Dimer (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - The Query, 1995-1998 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Red Rock, December 1999 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - TCU Press / Galveston notes / One Last Shot, 1993, 1998 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Thornton, Peter, March 1999 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Wall Street Journal / The Final Four, 1997-1998 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1977-1998
  This series contains correspondence regarding Cartwright's writing projects and those of others. The letters are arranged alphabetically. Notable correspondents include Bill Broyles, Cartwright family members, A.C. Greene, Stephen Harrigan, Ann Richards, and Bud Shrake as well as Playboy Magazine, Rolling Stone, and Texas Monthly.
  - A (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Adams, Randall Dale (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Atheneum (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - B (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Broyles, William (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - C (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Cartwright, Marge (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Cartwright, Shea (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Chagra, Vivian (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Cinco Puntos Press, April 1998 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Covert, Jean (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Crowder, A. Don (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Donovan, C. (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Dorman, Michael (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Emert, V. (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Forbes Magazine (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - Francis, Kevin (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - Glick, Allen (Box 15, Folder 21)
  - Green, Carl H. (Box 15, Folder 22)
  - Greene, A. C. (Box 15, Folder 23)
  - Harcourt Brace Jovanovich (Publishers) (Box 15, Folder 24)
  - Harrigan, Stephen (Box 15, Folder 25)
  - Haessler, George (Box 15, Folder 26)
  - ICM (Box 15, Folder 27)
  - Jensen (Box 15, Folder 28)
  - Jones, Bea (Box 15, Folder 29)
  - Kemper, William Priest (Box 15, Folder 30)
  - Kessler, Denise (Box 15, Folder 31)
  - L (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - M (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Marsh, Stanley (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Martin, Bill (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Mellett, Tom (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Mays, Prissy (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Mohler, Pat (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - P (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Playboy Magazine (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Progress Publishers (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - R (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - "Red, Ida" (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Richards, Ann (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Rinehart, John Paul (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Rolling Stone Magazine (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - S (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Sherrick, Lew (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Shrake, Bud (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Steinberg, Jo-Ann (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - Stephenson, (Tom?) (Box 16, Folder 20)
  - Texas Institute of Letters (Box 16, Folder 21)
  - Texas Monthly (Box 16, Folder 22)
  - Texas Monthly Press (Box 16, Folder 23)
  - Thompson, Leslie, 1998 (Box 16, Folder 24)
  - Universal Life Church (Box 16, Folder 25)
  - University of Texas at Arlington (Box 16, Folder 26)
  - W (Box 16, Folder 27)
  - Walk of the Stars (Box 16, Folder 28)
  - Weatherholt, Monty (Box 16, Folder 29)
  - Williams, Harold R. (Box 16, Folder 30)
  - Wyatt, Wyatt (Box 16, Folder 31)
  - Wyoming, Leo (Box 16, Folder 32)
  - No last name (Box 16, Folder 33)
- Clippings, 1976-1983
  This series contains newspaper clippings related to Cartwright's work.
  - Clippings, 1976-1983 (Box 16, Folder 34-35)